Ralph Henry Cameron papers, 1899-1915
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Ralph Henry Cameron papers, 1899-1915
AZ 127
Cameron, Ralph H.
Correspondence and other papers relating chiefly to Cameron's term as U.S. Delegate, Arizona statehood, political appointments, bills, and projects. Grand Canyon material include letters and legal papers relating to Bright Angel Trail, mining claims, a proposed power project, 1907-1912, and four guest registers of Cameron's Hotel and Camps, 1903-1907.
2.3 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL:http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Delegate to the U.S. Congress from Arizona, 1909-1912; U.S. Senator, 1921-1927; and businessman, operated Cameron's Hotel and Camps and developed Bright Angel Trail at the Grand Canyon.
Organization
Organized into four series:
Series I: Statehood Correspondence, 1909-1911
Series II: Political Appointments, Bills and Projects, 1909-1912
Series III: General Correspondence and Personal Material, 1901-1915
Series IV: Grand Canyon Materials, 1899-1912
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence and other papers relating chiefly to Cameron's term as U.S. Delegate, Arizona statehood, political appointments, bills, and projects. Arizona statehood materials include congratulatory letters and telegrams; and petitions by citizens of Phoenix regarding right of recall of the judiciary. Political bills represented include the Gila River Project, 1910-1912; site for Federal building, Tucson, Ariz.; Grand Canyon Scenic Railroad bill, 1909-1911; Hamilton-Owen bill; and the Territorial Tax bill, 1910-1911.
Grand Canyon materials include letters and legal papers relating to Bright Angel Trail, mining claims, a proposed power project, 1907-1912, and four guest registers of Cameron's Hotel and Camps, 1903-1907. Correspondents include Territorial Gov. Richard E. Sloan, J.L. Hubbell, C.N. Cotton, Louisa Ferrall, Grand Canyon postmistress, Clarence Spaulding, operator of Indian Gardens, and E.L. Kolb, photographer. Also present are maps of Arizona national forests including Garces, Coconino, Prescott, and Chiricahua National Forests.
Access Terms
Cameron, Ralph Henry, 1863-1953 -- Archives
Sloan, Richard E., 1857- -- Correspondence
Hubbell, John Lorenzo -- Correspondence
Ferrall, Louisa -- Correspondence
Spaulding, Clarence -- Correspondence
Cotton, C. N. (Clinton Neal), 1859-1936 -- Correspondence
Kolb, E. L. (Ellsworth Leonardson), 1876- -- Correspondence
Mines and mineral resources -- Arizona -- Coconino County
Tourist camps, hostels, etc. -- Arizona -- Grand Canyon
Hotels -- Arizona -- Grand Canyon
Statehood (American politics)
Arizona
Arizona -- Politics and government -- To 1950
Arizona -- History -- Sources
Grand Canyon (Ariz.) -- History -- Sources
Gila River Region (N.M. and Ariz.) -- History -- 20th century -- Sources
Tucson (Ariz.) -- Buildings
Correspondence
Photoprints
Photographs
Guest Registers
Container List
- Series I: Statehood Correspondence, 1909-1911
  - Correspondence. 1909-1911 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
  - Miscellaneous Papers (including petitions relating to right of recall of the judiciary, clippings, etc.). 1909-1911 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II: Political Apointments, Bills and Projects, 1909-1912
  - Political Appointments: Assistant U.S. District Attorney. 1909 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Political Appointments: Governor. 1909 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Political Appointments: Justice of the Supreme Court, A.T. (Edward M. Doe). 1909 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Political Appointments: Justice of the Supreme Court, A.T. (E.W. Lewis). 1909 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Political Appointments: Postmaster, Willcox, A.T. 1909 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Political Appointments: U.S. Marshal. 1908-1909 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Political Appointments: U.S. Disrict Attoney (J.E. Morrison). 1909-1910 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Press Relations: Correspondence. 1909-1911 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Political Bills and Projects: Colorado Indian Reservation Mining Claims. 1910-1912 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Political Bills and Projects: Conservation of Timber Lands (Proclamations from the President of the United States). 1910 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Political Bills and Projects: Federal Building Site, Tucson, A.T. 1909-1912 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Political Bills and Projects: General Frank H. Hitchcock's Trip. 1909 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Political Bills and Projects: Gila River Project. 1910-1912 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Political Bills and Projects: Grand Canyon Scenic Railroad Bill. 1909-1911 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Political Bills and Projects: Hamilton-Owen Bill. 1910 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Political Bills and Projects: Territorial Tax Bill. 1910-1911 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Political Bills and Projects: Miscellaneous 1911 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Includes:
    Apache Cavalry Unit, 1911.
    Town of Fredonia and the Indian Reservation, 1910.
    J.A. Mellon claim for loss of the schooner "Martha Washington" at the mouth of the Colorado River.
    "Arizona's Deep Sea Harbor."
    Petitions for a National Game Preserve, Santa Catalina Division of the Coronado National Forest.
    Petition and affidavits pertaining to certain property selected by the Santa Fe Pacific Railroad Company under Moqui Indian Scrip Location, 1911.
- Series III: General Correspondence and Personal Materials, 1901-1915
  - Miscellaneous Personal Material (photographs, clippings, political memorabilia, account book). 1901-1915 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence. 1904-1911, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
- Series IV: Grand Canyon Materials, 1899-1912
  - Grand Canyon Correspondence (Bright Angel Trail, mining claims, life and times at the Canyon.) 1901-1914 (Box 4, Folder 5-7)
  - Grand Canyon Power Project Correspondence. 1907-1912 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Grand Canyon Miscellaneous Papers. 1899-1912 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Grand Canyon Legal Papers. 1899-1903, 1906-1907, 1909-1912 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    Includes: Registers for Cameron's Hotel and Camps, 1903-1906.
  - Registers for Cameron's Hotel and Camps. 1906-1907 (Box 6)